Guide to the Filippo Tommaso Marinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Letters to and about Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1898-1970; Series III; 4.25; (10 boxes)
  - Sebastiani, Osvaldo to FTM
    - n.d. S.E. capo governo aderendo desidero... Telegram; No year Jan 25 Telegram; 1932 Dec 28 Telegram; 1934 Jan ? Telegram; 1934 May 18 Telegram; 1934 Jul 2 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 998)
    - 1934 Oct 21 Telegram; 1934 Dec 28 Telegram; 1935 Mar 10 Telegram; 1935 May 14 Telegram; 1935 Aug 22 1 p. TLS; 1939 May 21 Telegram (All correspondence signed "Segretario particolare Sebastiani")
  - Segantini, Bianca to FTM
    - 1922 Nov 14 4 p. (Box 16, Folder 999)
  - Selvaggi, Rito to the Congresso Futurista
    - 1924 Nov 21 1 p. On stationery of Il Teatro Illustrato. (Box 16, Folder 1000)
  - Seneca to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1001)
  - Serge, Dino (Pitigrilli, pseud.) to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1002)
  - Sèstito, Manlio to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 21 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1003)
  - Settimelli, Emilio
    See: Box 9, folder 275
  - Severini, Gino to FTM
    - 1910 May 17 4 p.; 1910 Oct 17 4 p. (Box 16, Folder 1004)
    - 1910 Oct 21 Postcard; 1910 Nov 15 Postcard; 1911 Jan 18 4 p.; [1912] Jun 10 4 p. Blue pencil marks on page 4.; [1912] Aug 5 3 p.; 1912 Aug 9 1 p.; 1912 Nov 25 2 p.; 1912 Dec 9 4 p. Top left of page 1 crossed out in blue pencil
    - 1913 Jan 22 Postcard; 1913 Jan 28 4 p.; [1913] Feb 1 Postcard; 1913 Feb 9 4 p.; 1913 Mar 12 1 p.; 1913 Mar 31 6 p.; [1913?] Apr 5 Postcard; [1913?] Apr 7 7 p.
    - 1913 Apr 19 4 p.; 1913 Jul 9 4 p.; 1913 Jul 17 4 p.; 1913 Jul 18 4 p.; 1913 Aug 6 4 p.; 1913 Aug 12 2 p.; [1913] Aug Postcard
    - 1913 Oct 11 3 p.; 1913 Oct 16 4 p.; 1913 Oct 22 2 p.; 1913 Nov 3 4 p. Upper portion of second sheet is cut off; 1913 Nov 10 4 p. "Rispondi al più presto, ti prego" in red pencil on page 4.; 1913 Dec 24 Postcard; [1914] (marked as 1913) Jan 7 4 p.; 1914 Jan 24 Postcard; 1914 Feb 19 3 p.; 1914 Feb 23 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1005)
    - 1914 Mar 13 Postcard; 1914 Mar 23 2 p.; 1914 Mar 28 3 p.; 1914 Mar 31 4 p.; 1914 Apr 9 4 p.; 1914 Apr 22 4 p.; 1914 Apr 26 4 p.; 1914 May 14 Postcard; 1914 Jul 4 Postcard
    - [1914] Jul 20 Postcard; 1914 Aug 6 3 p.; 1914 Aug 19 4 p.; 1914 Sep 1 6 p.; 1914 Nov 28 4 p.; 1915 Jan 1 6 p.; 1915 Jan 2 Postcard; 1915 Jan 22 1 p.; 1915 Mar 1 3 p.; 1930 Apr 17/26 8 p.
  - Severini, Gino to BCM
    - 1950 Mar 26 3 p. (Box 16, Folder 1006)
  - Silva, Luigi to FTM?
    - 1924 Nov 19 Card (Box 16, Folder 1007)
  - Sindacato Nazionale Autori e Scrittori to FTM's family
    - 1944 Dec 4 Telegram; signed "Il Commisserio Nazionale Bonelli' (Box 16, Folder 1008)
  - Sindaco Tolmezzo Candussio
    See: Box 8, folder 243
  - Singer, S. to FTM?
    - No year Jul 28 Ho ricevuto il dono cortesissimo... 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1009)
  - Sironi, Mario to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 3 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1010)
  - Skouenborg, Sigrid to BCM
    - [1944 Dec] Noi abbiamo sentito della vostra... Card (Box 16, Folder 1011)
  - Skouenborg, Vilhelm to BCM
    - [1944 Dec] Card (Box 16, Folder 1012)
  - Sodini, Angelo to FTM
    - 1924? Nov 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1013)
  - Soffici, Ardengo to FTM
    - No year "Sabato" Son felice di vedere... 4 p.; 1910 Jun 9 2 p.; 1912 Aug 3 3 p.; 1913 Mar 14 4 p. Note on page 4 by Papini; 1913 Apr 6 4 p. (Box 16, Folder 1014)
    - 1913 Jun 6 Postcard; 1913 Jul 19 4 p.; 1913 Aug 2 4 p. Underlinings in red pencil, p. 1.; 1914 Apr 28 2 p.; 1914 Aug 1 Postcard
  - Soggetti, Gino to FTM
    - 1922 Jul 4 2 p.; 1922 Jul 24 3 p.; 1929 Mar 21 1 p. Signed also by Teresa Soggetti (Box 16, Folder 1015)
  - Soldati, A[tanasio] to FTM
    - 1937 Feb 28 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1016)
  - Sollazzo to BCM
    - [1944] 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1017)
  - Sollazzo, Elsa to BCM
    - [1944] Dec 5 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1018)
  - Sollazzo, Elsa to Ala, Vittoria, Luce
    - [1944] Dec 5 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1018a)
  - Somma, Umberto to FTM
    - 1936 May 16 2 p. TLS; 1936 Jun 17 2 p. TLS; 1939 Oct 28 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1019)
  - Sonzogno, Casa Musicale to FTM
    - 1919 Feb 15 1 p. TLS; 1927? Jul 9 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1020)
  - Soratelli, E. Gaetani to FTM
    - 1909 Aug 23 Postcard (Box 16, Folder 1021)
  - Soresina, Mario to FTM?
    - 1924 Nov 19 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1022)
  - Sortino-Bona to FTM
    - 1922 Nov 22 Telegram; 1929 Mar 22 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1023)
  - Spacco, Giuseppe
    See: Box 11, folder 565
  - Spadafora to FTM?
    - 1939 April 18 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1024)
  - Spadanuda, Angelo to Primo Congresso Futurista
    - 1924 Nov 21 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1025)
  - Spano, M.G. to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 4 1 p.; 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1026)
  - Spavènta, Filippi Silvio to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1027)
  - Spazzapan
  - Spetia di Radione, Maggiore Conte to FTM's family
    - 1944 Dec 11 Card (Box 16, Folder 1028)
  - Spinelli, Giuseppe to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 5 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1029)
  - Spirindelli, Federico to BCM
    - [1929 Dec 25] card (Box 16, Folder 1030)
  - Squilloni, Gino to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1031)
  - Starace, Achille to FTM
    - 1937 Dec 7 Telegram; 1939 Feb 22 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1032)
  - Stefanini to FTM's Family
    - 1944 Dec 5 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1033)
  - Steiner, Giuseppe to Umberto Notari
    - 1934 Mar 30 1 p.; 1934 Apr 4 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1034)
  - Steiner, Giuseppe to BCM
    - 1935 Oct 30 Telegram; 1944 Dec 3 Telegram; 1944 Dec 4 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1035)
  - Steiner, Margherita to BCM
    - [1944] Dec 5 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1036)
  - Stemfity, Piera
  - Steno, Flavia to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 21 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1037)
  - Stern, Mme Louis to FTM?
    - n.d. avec ses meilleurs et plus chaleureux... Card (Box 16, Folder 1038)
  - Straufi, Ettore to Comitato per le Onoranze Nazionali a Filippo Tommaso Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 21 2 p. On the stationery of the Società del Giardino of Milan, the director. (Box 16, Folder 1039)
  - Stroppa, Maria Cristina to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1040)
  - Sugja, Antun to BCM?
    - [1944? Dec?] Card (Box 16, Folder 1041)
  - Swinburne, Algernon Charles to Madame Agresti
    - 1906 Oct 25 1 p. In English (Box 16, Folder 1042)
  - Sykora, Zlatan to BCM?
    - [1944? Dec?] Card (Box 16, Folder 1043)
  - Tamagnone to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (2 copies) (Box 16, Folder 1044)
  - Tamaro, Giorgio to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1045)
  - Tamaro, Giorgio to Ente Nazionale Artistico
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram signed also by Sambo and Vardabasso (Box 16, Folder 1045a)
  - Tamberi, Flaminio to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 22 4 p. (Box 16, Folder 1046)
  - Tanzi, G. to Comitato per le Onoranze a Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 25 1 p. On the stationery of the Times of India, Il Corrispondente per l'Italia (Box 16, Folder 1047)
  - Tapparelli to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 21 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1048)
  - Taquierdo, Jose Alberto to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 27 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1049)
  - Tarchi, [Angelo, 1897?- ] to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 7 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1050)
  - Tassinari, Antonio to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 28 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1051)
  - Tato (pseud. of Guglielmo Sansoni) to FTM
    - 1921 ? 28 Telegram 1921 Nov 17 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1052)
  - Taveggia, Angelo to FTM
    - 1913 May 15 1 p. (Box 16, Folder 1053)
  - Tavoiato Italo to FTM
    - 1914 Mar 22 4 p. (Box 16, Folder 1054)
  - Tedeschi, Geppo to FTM
    - 1940 Feb 5 Telegram; 1940 Feb 7 Telegram; 1940 Oct 12 Telegram; 1942 Sep 8 1 p. TLS, with note at bottom from Lina? Tedeschi; 1942 Sep 16 1 p. TLS; 1942 Oct 12 1 p. TLS (Box 16, Folder 1055)
  - Tedeschi, Geppo to BCM
    - 1940 Feb 28 Telegram; 1950 Jan 23 1 p. With note at bottom from Lina Tedeschi (Box 16, Folder 1055a)
  - Tegon to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1056)
  - Tempestini to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 16, Folder 1057)
  - Tenditta, Mario to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 1 p.; 1940 Aug 30 2 p. TLS, enclosure: letter from Mario Tenditta to Lucio Caracciolo d'Aquara,; 1940 Aug 30 1 p. TL, carbon (Box 16, Folder 1058)
  - Teobaldo, Mariotti
    See: Box 12, folder 579
  - Tergardia, Franco to FTM
    - No year "Agosto" Debbo ringraziarti per il tuo... 3 p.; No year "Agosto 14" Ho riletto Gli Indomabili 2 p.; 1922 Aug 10 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 1059)
  - Testoni, Alfredo to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1060)
  - Thayaht, Ernesto, pseud.
    See: Box 13, folder 746
  - Thore, René to FTM
    - No year "Juillet 10" Merci mille fois... 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1061)
  - Tirazzoli to lnnocenzo Cappa
    - 1922 Jan 14 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1062)
  - Titina, Margherita Maria to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1063)
  - Toddi to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 25 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1064)
  - Toghetti, Giovanni
    See: Box 17, folder 1072
  - Togo, Séizi to FTM
    - n.d. I beg to thank you for your letter... 2 p.; n.d. J'ai reçu votre lettre... 2 p.; n.d. Mille fois merci... 2 p.; n.d. Joyeux Noël... 1 p.; n.d. I am in receipt your letter... 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1065)
    - 1922 Jan 9 1 p.; 1922 Feb 9 2 p.; 1922 Feb 21 2 p.; 1922 Mar 2 1 p. Ripped in middle at both sides; 1922 Jun 21 2 p.
  - Toli, Rossana
  - Tomasello, Pietro to FTM
    - 1929 Apr 1 Card (Box 17, Folder 1066)
  - Tomellini, Toefarbea to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 25 4 p. (Box 17, Folder 1067)
  - Tommasini, Vittorio Osvaldo to FTM (Farfa, pseud.)
    - n.d. Prego comunicarci per ragioni... 2 p. Signed also by Acquaviva; 1942 Aug 24 1 p.; 1942 Sep 2 2 p.; 1942 Oct 9 2 p.; [1943 Dec 19] Postcard (Box 17, Folder 1068)
    - 1944 Jan 18 7 p.; 1944 Feb 19 1 p.; 1944 Mar 4 Postcard; signed also by Acquaviva; 1944 Mar 25 1 p.; 1944 Nov 4 Postcard; 1944 Dec 13 Postcard; enclosed in an envelope to BCM; signed also by Acquaviva
      See also: Box 7, folder 72
  - Tonini to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1069)
  - Torres, Duilio to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1070)
  - Tortarolo, Bianco to FTM
    - 1940 Sep 26 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1071)
  - Toghetti, Giovanni to FTM
    - 1909 Aug 27 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1072)
  - Tozzi, Giorgio to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 28 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1073)
  - Trafeli, Carissimo to FTM
    - 1929 Apr 19 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1074)
  - Tramonte, Giuseppe to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 25 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1075)
  - Traverlo, Giuliana
    See: Box 7, folder 72
  - Traversi, Giannino Antona to Comitato Onoranze Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1076)
  - Treves to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1077)
  - Trillini to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1078)
  - Trilussa to FTM
    - n.d. non dimenticare che desidero... 1 p. "R" marked in red pencil (Box 17, Folder 1079)
      See also: Series IV, Box 27, folder 1381
  - Trimarco to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1080)
  - Trimarco to Comitato Onoranze Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1081)
  - Troilo, Achille to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1082)
  - Tumminelli, Calogero to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1083)
  - Turati, Filippo to FTM
    - 1909 Feb 6 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1084)
  - Umani, Giorgio to FTM
    - 1934 Sep 16 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1085)
  - Umberto di Savoia to FTM
    - 1937 Mar 2 Telegram; 1940 Mar 7 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1086)
  - Ungaretti, Giuseppe to FTM
    - No year Aug 30 1 p.; 1914 Aug 9 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1087)
  - Usigli, Gastone to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1088)
  - Vacarescu, Elena to FTM
    - n.d. Pardonnez à une voyageuse... 1 p. TLS; with corrections in black ink; signed Hélène Vacaresco Blue pencil marks at top: "Prosa 10" n.d. ...je suis chez ma cousine... 4 p. (Box 17, Folder 1089)
  - Valdagne, Pierre to FTM
    - n.d. avec mes remercîments les plus... Card (Box 17, Folder 1090)
  - Valdani to FTM
    - 1926 Jun 6 Fascisti italiani salutano... Telegram; 1926 Jun 6 circolo italiano saluta ardente... Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1091)
  - Valente, Manette to BCM
    - n.d. [Dec 1944] ci uniamo al suo grande... Card, signed also by Anna Carmeli and Cari Benfereri (Box 17, Folder 1092)
  - Valentinelli, Ennio to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 26 1 p. Newspaper clipping "Le onoranze a Marinetti" cut up and pasted to page (Box 17, Folder 1093)
  - Valenza, G.B. to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 28 2 p. Signed also by Giuseppe De Filippis (Box 17, Folder 1094)
  - Valeri
  - Vallauri, Giancarlo to BCM
    - 1944 [Dec 5] 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1095)
  - Vallette, Mme Alfred to FTM (pseud. Rachilde)
    - 1908 Mar 6 1 p. In French; 1908 [Apr 4] 1 p. In French (Box 17, Folder 1096)
  - Valli, Giacomo to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram signed also by Leo Valli; 1929 Mar 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1097)
  - Valli, Giacomo to Comitato Onoranze Nazionale a Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram signed also by Leo Valli (Box 17, Folder 1098)
  - Valois, Georges? to FTM
    - 1926 Oct 10 1 p. In French; 1926 Oct 26 Telegram, in French (Box 17, Folder 1099)
  - Valorabe, Cliptio to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 5 1 p. Typed poem, "In morte di Marinetti" with written note to BCM on same page (Box 17, Folder 1100)
  - Valori, Aldo
    See: Box 8, folder 178
  - Valoti, Rosetta to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 28 Card (Box 17, Folder 1101)
  - Valvassori, Peroni to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 26 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1102)
  - Van Dooren, J. to FTM
    - 1909 Mar 28 3 p. In French (Box 17, Folder 1103)
  - Varaldo to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram; signed "Varaldo et Gabbio" (Box 17, Folder 1104)
  - Vardabasso
    See: Box 16, folder 1045
  - Varvaro to Comitato Onoranze Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 22 Telegram; signed Varvaro, Caramusa, Calderone, Pippo Rizzo (Box 17, Folder 1105)
  - Vecchi, Ferruccio to FTM
    - 1923 Nov 9 2 p.; 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1106)
  - Vecchi, Omero to FTM (pseud. Luciano Folgore)
    - n.d. Come avrai visto dalla lettera... 2 p.; n.d. Ho ricevuto il tuo magnifico... 10 p.; n.d. Attendo la copertina, A me piacerebbe... 2 p.; 1909 Aug 4 Postcard; 1910 Feb 3 2 p.; 1911 Jun 20 3 p.; 1914 Apr 18 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1107)
  - Vella to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 25 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1108)
  - Venerandi, Antonio to FTM
    - 1924 Nov 28 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1109)
  - Veneziani, Carlo to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1110)
  - Venturini to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 2 1 p. Enclosure: 1 page letter to BCM from Anna Venturini (Box 17, Folder 1111)
  - Verderame Sapio, Luigi to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 24 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1112)
  - Verga, Giuseppe to FTM
    - 1908 Mar 17 3 p.; 1908 Mar 28 2 p.; 1908 Aug 11 2 p.; 1909 Nov 8 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1113)
  - Vergani, Orio to FTM
    - 1939 Jul 1 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1114)
  - Verhaeren, Emile to FTM
    - n.d. Oui, votre revue est bien faite... 3 p.; 1905 Sep 5 2 p. On page 2 a poem (Box 17, Folder 1115)
  - Verona
    See: Box 8, folder 166
  - Veronese, Ugo to FTM
    - 1940 Nov 13 2 p. On page 2, a note from another person (Box 17, Folder 1116)
  - Verossi to FTM
    - 1940 Oct 16 2 p. Enclosure: postcard with ALS on verso (Box 17, Folder 1117)
  - Vespignani
    See: Box 15, folder 931
  - Vidussoni to FTM
    - n.d. Vivamente ringrazioti per cordiale... Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1118)
  - Viejo, R.
    See: Box 7, folder 149
  - Vieri to FTM?
    - No year Jun 18 Ho ricevuto la tua risposta... 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1119)
  - Viggiani, N to FTM
    - n.d. Confermovi conferenza santos... Telegram; n.d. Recevi telegramma reduci... Telegram n.d. Istruii mio rappresentante... Telegram n.d. Curytiba non accetto condizioni... Telegram; 1926 Jan 15 2 p. TLS (Box 17, Folder 1120)
  - Villanova, Antonio e Anna Maria to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 7 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1121)
  - Villaroel to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 21 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1122)
  - Viola to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 21 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1123)
  - Visan, Tancrède de to FTM
    - 1937 Apr 30 3 p. In French (Box 17, Folder 1124)
  - Visconti di Modrone, La Duchessa to FTM
    - n.d. Con mille ringraziamenti... Card (Box 17, Folder 1125)
  - Vittorio Emanuele III, King of Italy to FTM
    - 1937 Feb 28 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1126)
  - Viva, Anna
    See: Box 7, folder 172
  - Vivanti, Amie to FTM
    - n.d. Mille grazie. Venga, se vuole,... 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1127)
  - Viviani, Alberto to FTM
    - 1942 Sep 5 2 p. Page 2 contains note and drawing by another person - Pia Viviani (Box 17, Folder 1128)
  - Viviani, Pia to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 2 1 p. Enclosure: 1 page ALS from Alberto Viviani (Box 17, Folder 1129)
  - Vogüé, Eugène Melchior, Vicomte de to FTM
    - n.d. avec ses remerciements... Card n.d. avec ses remerciements à Monsieur Filippo Tommaso Marinetti... Card (Box 17, Folder 1130)
  - Volpi di Misurata, Giuseppe
    See: Box 12, folder 601
  - Volt to FTM
    - n.d. sono qui ora con la famiglia... 4 p.; n.d. non potendo intervenire personalment... 3 p. (Box 17, Folder 1131)
  - Von Plessen, Johann, Baron to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 2 1 p. Enclosure: Card (Box 17, Folder 1132)
  - Vossler, K. to FTM
    - 1914 Jul 28 4 p., Vossler, Karl, 1872-1949 (Box 17, Folder 1133)
  - Werner?, René to FTM
    - n.d. Pardonnez à un voyageur de ne... Postcard (Box 17, Folder 1134)
  - Willuhott, A to FTM
    - 1909 Sep 23 Postcard (Box 17, Folder 1135)
  - Wolfe, Humbert to FTM
    - 1936 Jan 6 1 p. In French (Box 17, Folder 1136)
  - Zamara, Guido to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 1 p. TLS (Box 17, Folder 1137)
  - Zanzani, Licurgo to Ente Italiano Artistico
    - 1924 Nov 20 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1138)
  - Zanzi, Emilio to BCM
    - 1944 Dec 4 3 p. (Box 17, Folder 1139)
  - Zaratin
  - Zátkova, Rougena. d.1923 to FTM
    - n.d. Finito di leggere il libro "Come si seducono le donne"... 2 p.; n.d. Cristallo viola: Sono fino, fino... 2 p.; n.d. Sono molto impressionata da "Re Baldoria"... 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1140)
    - 1920 Mar 21 1 p.; 1920 Apr 1 2 p.; 1920 May 12 3 p.; 1921 Oct 3 2 p.; 1921 Dec 6 2 p.
    - See also: Box 8, folder 259 and Box 13, folder 684
  - Zátkova, Rougena, d.1923 to BCM
    - n.d. esporre volontieri i tre ritratti... 1 p. (Box 17, Folder 1141)
  - Zazzarini, Nello to Congresso Futurista Milano
    - 1924 Nov 23 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1142)
  - Zelaschigru, Sandra to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 27 2 p. (Box 17, Folder 1143)
  - Zicàri, Antonio Franco to Comitato Nazionale Onoranze a Marinetti
    - 1924 Nov 20 2 p. Enclosure: Card (Box 17, Folder 1144)
  - Zimei, Isa to FTM
    - 1944 Nov 18 3 p. (Box 17, Folder 1145)
  - Zoli, Corrado to FTM
    - 1919 Jan 12 Postcard (Box 17, Folder 1146)
  - Zopegni, Carola to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram signed also by Giuseppe Zopegni (Box 17, Folder 1147)
  - Zoppis, Luigi to FTM
    - 1909 Oct 9 Card (Box 17, Folder 1148)
  - Zozzoli, Adolfo to FTM
    - n.d. vivissimi rallegramenti... card (Box 17, Folder 1149)
  - Zucco, Mario to FTM
    - 1929 Mar 22 Telegram (Box 17, Folder 1150)
      See also: Box 13, folder 729
  - Zuii, Bruno
- Writings by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, 1895-1944; Series IV; 11.5; (28 boxes)
  - WRITINGS
    - A Mlle Bice Catinello
      - Autograph manuscript sonnet, signed. Heavily corrected. Milan, Jan 27, 1897. 1 p. (Box 18, Folder 1151)
    - A protezione dell'abbeverata
      - Autograph manuscript in an unidentified hand, with corrections in ink and pencil by FTM. 11 p. (Box 18, Folder 1152)
    - A une étoile
      - Autograph manuscript poem. On verso of p. 5: "Belle Etoile". 5 p. (Box 18, Folder 1153)
    - Les abimes de la mer
      - Autograph manuscript poem. 1 p. (Box 18, Folder 1154)
    - "'Gli adorati della Patria' di Geppo Tedeschi e la teoria polemica del romanzo sintetico"
      - Printed version, Autori e Scrittori, 1941 Oct (Box 18, Folder 1155)
    - Aeromusica dell'alfabeto in libertá, Manifesto Futurista, by Filippo Tommaso Marinetti and Tullio Crali
      - Typescript with a few manuscript corrections 1944. 6 p., plus cover title (Box 18, Folder 1156)
    - [L'Aeroplano]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for an essay on airplanes, with references to Budapest. 2 p. (Box 18, Folder 1157)
    - L'aeropoema del Golfo della Spezia
      - Proof with pencil corrections. 85 p., numbered in MS 1-7, in type 3-90. Missing pages 10, 18, 20, 38, 40, 51-58, 60. (Box 18, Folder 1158)
    - L'aeropoema del Golfo della Spezia
      - Proof with pencil corrections. 84 p., renumbered by FTM 33-125. (Box 18, Folder 1159)
    - [Aeropoema del Golfo della Spezia]
      - Autograph manuscript notes for the poem. 4 p. (Box 18, Folder 1160)
    - L'aeropoema dell'assurda sospensione
      - Autograph manuscript poem, with corrections. 4 p. (Box 18, Folder 1161)
    - L'aeropoema di Gesù.
      - Poem, in the hand of BCM 90 p. (Box 18, Folder 1162)
    - L'aeropoema futurista dei Mas di Costanzo Ciano
      - Poem in his secretary's hand, with corrections by FTM. 59 p. (Box 18, Folder 1163)
    - L'aeropoema vissuto della rivoluzione fascista
      - Autograph manuscript poem. 107 p., in poor condition, edges frayed (Box 18, Folder 1164)
    - [Aeropoesia]
      - Untitled autograph manuscript poem, beginning O poeti tradizionali (Box 18, Folder 1165)
        See also: Box 22, folder 1268; Box 25, folder 1338; Box 35, folder 1601; Box 36, folder 1616; Box 36, folder 1630; Box 40, folder 1692
      - Autograph manuscript notes, originally found with Sur Milan Zang Tumb Tumb]'. 13 p. (Box 18, Folder 1166)
      - Autograph manuscript notes 4 p., originally found with a letter to Bonfinto. On the verso of a fragment of a typescript essay in German about art (Box 18, Folder 1167)
      - Autograph manuscript notes beginning: 'Autour de la cathédrale...' 1 p. (Box 18, Folder 1168)
      - Autograph manuscript notes. 4 p., numbered 1-4. (Box 18, Folder 1169)
    - "Aeropoesia e aeropittura Maringuerra nel libro di Giovanni Acquaviva"
      - Printed version, Autori e Scrittori, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 1170)
    - [Aeropoeti futuristi]
      - Autograph manuscript essay on futurist 'aeropoeti' Signed on last page. With a few corrections. 2 p. (Box 18, Folder 1171)
    - [L'aeroscienza poetificata]
      - Autograph manuscript notes with corrections Heading at the top of first page. A proposal for the foundation of a political/scientific society. 6 p. (Box 18, Folder 1172)
    - Gli affari del primo porto Mediterraneo Genova
      - Autograph manuscript play, in ink with corrections in pencil. 47 p. (Box 18, Folder 1173)
    - [African trip]
      - Autograph manuscript comments, notes and obser- vations about Africa. Probably about 1932. 75 p., numbered 1-72 [missing pp. 48-51] (Box 18, Folder 1174)
    - [African war]
      - Autograph manuscript notes. 25-26 Jan and 28 Feb 1936. 4 p. (Box 18, Folder 1175)
    - Agello Castaldi [Fiat] 709
      - Autograph manuscript poem, in French. Apparently an earlier version of IV.1.12. On verso: 'Agello Castaldi Fiat 709 Abozzo' in hand of FTM. 29 p. (Box 18, Folder 1176)
        See also: Box 34, folders 1579-80
    - Agello Castaldi Fiat 709, Aeropoesie en Mots en Liberté.
      - Autograph manuscript poem, apparently a later version of IV.1.11. 38 p. (Box 18, Folder 1177)
        See also: Box 34, folder 1579-80
      - Autograph manuscript poem signed by FTM. Apparently another copy of IV.1.12. On verso: title and [Dedication?] 38 p. (Box 18, Folder 1178)
    - L'Alcova d'Acciaio
      - Autograph manuscript in an unidentified hand, with corrections by FTM. Labelled by FTM at the top of p. 1, 'Dall'Alcova d'Acciaio'. This fragment corresponds to Chapter XX, 'Le forze della gioia, della pietà e della vendetta', of L'Alcova d'Acciaio (Milan, Casa Editrice Vitagliano, 1921). MS pp. 1-6 (line 11) are the published pp. [237]-239 (line 3); MS pp. 6 (line 13) - 12 are the published pp. 241-243 (line 11). 12 p. (Box 18, Folder 1179)
    - "Ali d'Italia"
      - Printed version, Bordata, 1931 Mar 1
        See: Oversize Box 54, folder 2000